Guide to the Russian State Military Archives Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- German-Soviet Military Cooperation, 1918-1934; Series I
  - Letter from V.Kh. Tairov to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1930 February 16; 174 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Letter from V.Kh. Tairov, the Dep. Chief of the 4th Directorate of the Red Army Staff, to K.Ye. Voroshilov with a petition about alloting duty-free or preferential tariffs to the Germans working at the joint enterprises in the USSR for the transport of baggage. Original.
  - Report N° 029025/ss. from V.Kh. Tairov to Voroshilov, 1930 February 21; 175 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Report N° 029025/ss. from V.Kh. Tairov to Voroshilov with a request to indicate which line to hold in talks with the Germans concerning tank building. Original with a resolution by Voroshilov.
  - Report N° 029024/ss. from Tairov to Voroshilov, 1930 February 21; 176 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Report N° 029024/ss. from Tairov to Voroshilov on the approval for a program of acquainting General Halm with the Red Army. Original with a resolution by Voroshilov.
  - Conversation of Uborevich with Hammer, 1930 February 30; 177 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Extract from a recording of a conversation of Uborevich with Hammer. Copy.
  - Letter from Putna to Voroshilov, 1930 March 18; 178 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Letter from Putna to Voroshilov on the worsening of relations with Germany and on the danger of an attack on the USSR.
  - Memo report N°029157/ss. to Voroshilov, 1930 March 20; 179 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Memo report N°029157/ss. to Voroshilov on the acquainting of a group of Red Army officers with the means of communication of the Reichswehr. Copy with a resolution by Voroshilov.
  - Letter from Putna to Voroshilov, 1930 March 27; 180 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Letter from Putna to Voroshilov on the worsening of relations with Germany. Copy.
  - Extract from letter from Putna to Voroshilov, 1930 April 16; 181 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Extract from a letter from Putna to Voroshilov on the complication of relations with Germany. Copy.
  - Memo report from management of "Aviatrest", 1930 April 28; 182 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Memo report from management of the State Trust for Aviation Industry "Aviatrest" to the Directorate of Affairs of the RVS on technical collaboration with BMW, Gnomie Rohn, Heinkel, and with the design group Rieschor [sp.].
  - Report from Kurkov to the Directorate of Affairs of the RVS, 1930 May 8; 183 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Report from Kurkov, Dep. Chief of the Naval Forces of the Red Army, to the Directorate of Affairs of the RVS on the extent of technical assistance from the firms Atlas Werke and Elektroakustik. Original.
  - Report from Alksnis to Voroshilov, 1930 May 15; 184 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Report from Alksnis to Voroshilov (copies to Unshlikht, Shaposhnikov, Baranov, Uborevich and Berzin) on [his] participation in military-air games in the city of Beyreuth, Germany. Original.
  - Letter from Ludwig to Uborevich, 1930 May 17; 185 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Letter from Ludwig to Uborevich on the question of technical assistance for the USSR. Copy.
  - Memo report from engineer Broverma, 1930 May 30; 186 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Memo report from engineer Broverman to the Chief of the Directorate of Mechanization and Motorization of the Red Army on the arranging of educational matters at TEKO. Original.
  - Report from Alksnis to the Dep. Chairman of the RVS, 1930 October 2; 187 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Report from Alksnis to the Dep. Chairman of the RVS on a test by the VVS USSR of a model of motor with air cooling made by Siemens. Original.
  - Protocol from the Bureau International Accounts, 1930 December 1; 188 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Protocol from the Bureau for International Accounts in the Currency Sector of the Narkom for Finance of the USSR. Copy.
  - Draft contract, 1930 December 16; 189 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Draft contract concerning the change of the Consortium Contract of Deruluft and on the concessionary terms of the operation of air lines by Deruluft. Certified copy.
  - Letter from Dr. Schkener, 1930 December 21; 190 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Letter from Dr. Schkener the manager of the frrm Zeppelin "On the question of dirigible-building and air service using dirigibles of the Zeppelin type in Russia and Siberia".
  - Letter from Putna to Voroshilov, 1930 October 30; 191 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Letter from Putna to Voroshilov on the possibility granted by General Hammerstein for studying staff work in the Reichswehr. Original with a resolution by Voroshilov.
  - Memo report N° 031014/ss. from Berzin to Shaposhnikov, 1931 January 5; 192 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Memo report N° 031014/ss. from Berzin to Shaposhnikov concerning a question raised by the Currency Directorate of the NKF USSR on weapons that were seized by the Germans after the armistice at Brest. Original.
  - Survey on tanks, 1931 January 30; 193 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Survey drawn up by a weapons department on tanks produced by Rheinmetall. Original (in German).
  - Report N° G2058, 1931 March 15; 194 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Report N° G2058 on the results of the work done by the Tomko station, sent by the German representatives in accordance with a request by I.P. Uborevich, the Dep. Chairman of the RVS. Original (in German).
  - Invitation to G.V. Akimov, 1931 May 9; 195 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Invitation to G.V. Akimov professor at TsAGI, to take part in a congress of the German Bunsen Society and a German society of applied chemistry. Translated from German. Copy.
  - Report N° 452/s. from Ya.I. Alksnis to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1931 May 17; 196 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Report N° 452/s. from Ya.I. Alksnis to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the official sending of TsAGI engineers G.V. Akimov and V.O. Krening to a congress of the German Bunsen Society. Original.
  - Letter N° Gn-5104 from V.K. Putna to Uborevich, 1931 May 26; 197 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Letter N° Gn-5104 from V.K. Putna from 19 May 1931 to Uborevich on the work of a group of Soviet commanders. Certified copy.
  - Letter from a German engineer to I.P. Uborevich expressing [his] thanks, 1931 May 28; 198 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Original (in German).
  - Letter N° 147/31 from Yakovenko to Uborevich, 1931 June 4; 199 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Letter N° 147/31 from Yakovenko, the military attache in Germany, to Uborevich on a reception with General Adam and on conversations with General Hammerstein. Certified copy.
  - Letter N° 148/31 from Yakovenko to Uborevich, 1931 June 5; 200 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Letter N° 148/31 from Yakovenko to Uborevich on a conversation with General Hammer. Certified copy.
  - Letter from A.I. Yegorov to Voroshilov, 1931 June 8; 201 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Letter from A.I. Yegorov, the Chief of Staff, to Voroshilov with a request to invite two officers of the Reichswehr General Staff as instructors in the military academy. Original.
  - Information N° 20/872s. from V.M. Gittis, 1931 June 11; 202 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Information N° 20/872s. from V.M. Gittis, the plenipotentiary of the Narkomvoenmor at the Narkomvneshtorg of the USSR to A.G. Odov (in the Directorate of Mfairs of the RVS USSR) on orders for Heinkel ND55 airplanes. Original.
  - Information from N. Fedorov on Heinkel ND-37 fighter airplanes, 1931 June 13; 203 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Information from N. Fedorov, Chief of the UVVS of the Red Army to O. Urusov, the Head of the 1st Sector of the Directorate of Affairs of the NKVM and RVS USSR on the order for Heinkel ND-37 fighter airplanes. Original.
  - Letter N° 151/31 from Yakovenko to Tukhachevskii, 1931 June 15; 204 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Letter N° 151/31 from Yakovenko to Tukhachevskii, the Dep. Chairman of the RVS USSR, on the military-political situation in Germany and on a visit of a group of Soviet military specialists with generals of the Reichswehr. Certified copy.
  - Dispatch N° G-1189 from Ya.K. Berzin to Voroshilov, 1931 June 18; 205 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Dispatch N° G-1189 from Ya.K. Berzin to Voroshilov with the gist of an extract from a letter by Yakovenko.
  - Letter from V.K. Putna to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1931 July 2; 206 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Letter from V.K. Putna to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the official trip to the Reichswehr maneuvers of a group of Red Army commanders. Original.
  - Document in German, 1931 July 28; 207 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letter N° 159/31 from Yakovenko, 1931 August 1; 208 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Letter N° 159/31 from Yakovenko from 1 August on Germany's foreign and domestic situation. Copy.
  - Information N° 01464s/s. on the delivery of armaments, 1931 August 21; 209 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Information N° 01464s/s. on the unsettled question of the line on the delivery of armaments; directed to Yefimov, Dep. Chief of Armaments. Certified copy.
  - Document in German, 1931 August 22; 210 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Original.
  - Letter N° 165/31 from Yakovenko to the UVO maneuvers, 1931 August 30; 211 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Extract from letter N° 165/31 from Yakovenko on the invitation of a German delegation to the UVO maneuvers.
  - Letter N° 165/31 from Yakovenko, 1931 August 30; 212 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Extract from letter N° 165/31 from Yakovenko on the results of a trip by the Reichswehr for firing practice. Certified copy.
  - Training account N° 2 from the Chief of the tank course at Kazan to M.N. Tukhachevskii, 1931 September 13; 213 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Training account N° 2 from the Chief of the tank course at Kazan to M.N. Tukhachevskii on the results of Soviet-German studies for the summer period. N° Gik-4283ss. Certified copy.
  - Letter N° 171/31 from Yakovenko, 1931 September 22; 214 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Extract from letter N° 171/31 from Yakovenko on the advisability of General Adam coming to the USSR. Copy.
  - Letter N° 171/31 from Yakovenko to M.N. Tukhachevskii, 1931 September 22; 215 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Extract from letter N° 171/31 from Yakovenko to M.N. Tukhachevskii on his conversation with General F. Fischer. Certified copy.
  - Report N° G-7154s/s, 1931 September 25; 216 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Copy of report N° G-7154s/s. on the results of an official trip to the Reichswehr of B.S. Gorbachev, Corps Commander-Commissar in the BUZ MVO. Certified copy.
  - Report N° G-7156s, 1931 October 3; 217 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Report N° G-7156s. from B.N. Ushinskii, instructor at KUKS "Vystrel" to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the results of an official trip to a unit of the German Reichswehr. Copy.
  - Protocol N° 10/1087 from the commission for the authorization of foreign flight through the USSR, 1931 October 8; 218 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Protocol N° 10/1087 from the commission for the authorization of foreign flight through the USSR on the flight of German pilot Ellie Beinhorn [sp]. Certified copy.
  - Report from Yefimov, Dep. Chief of Armaments, to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1931 October 30; 219 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Report from Yefimov, Dep. Chief of Armaments, to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the course of fulfilling the contract with Rheinmetall. Original.
  - Information about the talks of the Soviet and German sides concerning the work by Soviet-German enterprises, 1931 November; 220 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Information about the talks of the Soviet and German sides concerning the work by Soviet-German enterprises; compiled on the principal talks of the leadership of the NKVM and the Reichswehr. Copy.
  - Report from Berzin on the results of the work at the joint enterprises at Kazan, Lipetsk and at the Tomka station, 1931 November; 221 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Report from Berzin on the results of the work at the joint enterprises at Kazan, Lipetsk and at the Tomka station. Original.
  - Information about M.N. Tukhachevskii's reception with the German officers Adam, Kostring, Hofmeister and Manstein, 1931 November 10; 222 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Information about M.N. Tukhachevskii's reception with the German officers Adam, Kostring, Hofmeister and Manstein.
  - Record of K.Ye. Voroshilov's conversation with General Adam, 1931 November 19; 223 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Record of K.Ye. Voroshilov's conversation with General Adam, the Chief of Staff of the Reichswehr, on the military collaboration. Copy.
  - Letter N° 04237s/s. from General Adam to Voroshilov, 1931 December 8; 224 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Letter N° 04237s/s. from General Adam to Voroshilov on his impressions of the trip to army units. Original in German with trans.
  - Record N° 514611 of conversations of K.Ye. Voroshilov, M.N. Tukhachevskii and A.I. Yegorov, with von Dirksen, 1931 December 11; 225 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Record N° 514611 of conversations of K.Ye. Voroshilov, M.N. Tukhachevskii and A.I. Yegorov.with von Dirksen, the German ambassador. Certified copy.
  - Short description of Wilhelm Adam, Chief of the Truppen-amt, 1931 December 23; 226 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Short description of Wilhelm Adam, Chief of the Truppen-amt, compiled by the Officer for Foreign Dealings NKVM; with G.M. Shtern's personal impressions of Adam.
  - Excerpts from the letters of Red Army commanders who were sent on official trips to Germany on their participation in studies, 1931; 227 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Excerpts from the letters of Red Army commanders who were sent on official trips to Germany on [their] participation in studies (used by K.Ye. Voroshilov in his speech). On the documents are the marginal notes of K.Ye. Voroshilov.
  - Memo report N° G-35/s. from Roizenman to Voroshilov, 1932 January 5; 228 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Memo report N° 0-35/s. from Roizenman, member of the Presidium of the TsK VKP(b) to Voroshilov on the collaboration with Heinkel. Copy.
  - Report N° 6/12627/ss. from Rogovskii to Voroshilov, 1932 January 4; 229 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Report N° 6/12627/ss. from Rogovskii, Artillery Inspector addressed to Voroshilov with a petition for a group of officers to be sent to Germany on official trips.
  - Record of a conversation of S.I. Ventsov with Generals Blomberg and Schonheitz [sp.], 1932 February 5; 230 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Record of a conversation of S.I. Ventsov with Generals Blomberg and Schonheitz [sp.].
  - Note from Ya.B. Gamarnik to I.V. Stalin, 1932 July 14; 231 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Note from Ya.B. Gamarnik to I.V. Stalin with a petition for sending Red Army commanders to the Military Academy (of Germany). Certified copy.
  - Letter from K.Ye. Voroshilov to Piatakov, Dep. Narkomtiazhprom, 1932 July 28; 232 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Letter from K.Ye. Voroshilov to Piatakov, Dep. Narkomtiazhprom on the necessity to remove the Czech specialists from Lipetsk. Copy.
  - Memo report from M.N. Tukhachevskii to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1932 November 14; 233 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Memo report from M.N. Tukhachevskii to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the results of his trip to Germany. Certified copy.
  - Letter from the commander of the UVO to K.Yeo Vorshiloy, 1932 October 28; 234 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Letter from the commander of the UVO to K.Yeo Vorshiloy on the need to send P.P. Lebedev, the former Chief of the Red Army Staff, on an official trip to Germany for medical treatment. Original.
  - Letter from Voroshilov to Stalin, 1932 November 5; 235 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Letter from Voroshilov to Stalin with a request to approve the official trip of two Red Army commanders to Germany. Copy.
  - Biographical information N° 2013 for Colonel Hartmann, 1933 January 21; 236 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Biographical information N° 2013 for Colonel Hartmann, the Reichswehr military attaché. Copy.
  - Program speech N°58820 of A. Hitler, 1933 March 2; 237 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Program speech N°58820 of A. Hitler. Copy.
  - Letter N° 2-7040 from M.K. Levandovskii to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1933 March 17; 238 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Letter N° 2-7040 from M.K. Levandovskii to K.Ye. Voroshilov on his official trip to Germany. Copy.
  - Record of a conversation between N.N. Krestinskii, von Dirksen and Hartmann, 1933 April 3; 239 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Record of a conversation between N.N. Krestinskii, von Dirksen and Hartmann. Copy.
  - Report from V.N. Levichev to K.Yeo Voroshilov, 1933 April 18; 240 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Report from V.N. Levichev to K.Yeo Voroshilov on [his] inspection of educational institutions of the Reichswehr. Original.
  - Record of talks with representatives of the Red Army, 1933 June 8; 241 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Record of talks with representatives of the Red Army (material from the German military attache). Certified copy.
  - Letter N° G-I043 from V.N. Levichev, 1933 June 13; 242 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Letter N° G-I043 from V.N. Levichev from Germany. Copy.
  - Field trip conducted for those on official trips from the Reichswehr in 1933. N° 59562ss/Sh, 1933 June 22; 243 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Field trip conducted for those on official trips from the Reichswehr in 1933. N° 59562ss/Sh. Copy.
  - Letter from V.N. Levichev, 1933 June 19; 244 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Letter from V.N. Levichev from Germany. Copy.
  - Memo report N° 4175 from Hartmann to K.Ye. Voroshilov, 1933 June 26; 245 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Memo report N° 4175 from Hartmann to K.Ye. Voroshilov on the liquidation of the "friends'" enterprises at Lipetsk (also in German). Copy.
  - List N° 412, 1933 July 29; 246 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List N° 412 of property from the Kazan and Lipetsk stations liable for return transport to Germany. Copy.
  - List N° 4191, 1933 August 3; 247 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    List of property which ought to be sent from the USSR to Germany in connection with the liquidation of the "friends" station at Tomka.
  - Message from Hartmann, 1933 August 9; 248 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Message on the refusal to allow German officers to come to exercises of Red Army units.
  - Reception of von Dirksen, 1933 August 17; 249 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    From the diary of N.N. Krestinskii.
  - Information N° 60031 ss/Sh. on Soviet-German relations, 1933 September 4; 250 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Extract from a report from General Bockelberg on his trip through the USSR, 8-28 May 1933, 1933 September 26; 251 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Information N° 60237 on Germany's foreign political situation, 1933 October 8; 252 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Memo report N° 4234 from Ya. K. Berzin to K. Ye. Voroshilov, 1933 October 14; 253 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Memo on the course of liquidation of the "friends" enterprises at Tomka, Lipetsk and Kazan.
  - Reception of Nadolny, the German ambassador, 1933 November 29; 254 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    From the diary of N. N. Krestinskii.
  - Translation of a report from Hartmann on the Red Army, 1933 December 9; 255 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Secret service material N° 05 224 ss., 1933 December 13; 256 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    On the technical and numerical expansion of the Reichswehr.
  - Account of the plenipotentiary representative of the USSR in Germany, 1933 December 31; 257 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Material in German, 1934 January; 258 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - List of Red Army commanding officers who were in Germany on official trips from 1924 to 1936, Undated; 259 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Documents concerning the Use of Soviet Tanks in the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939; Series II (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
- Additional Material, 1921-1939; Accession 1997-M-036
  General
  Includes accession 1996-M-076 (See Box 8A).
  - Annual Reports of the NKVM (People's Commission for War and the Navy), 1921-1927
    - Annual Reports of the NKVM, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Annual Reports of the NKVM, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2, Folder 3)
    - 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 4, Folder 5)
    - 1923-1924 (Box 2, Folder 1, Folder 2)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 3, Folder 4)
    - 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 1, Folder 2, Folder 3)
    - 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Stenographic Reports of the RVS (Military Revolutionary Council), 1927-1938
    - 1927-1929 (Box 4)
    - 1930 (Box 5)
    - 1931-1933 (Box 6)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 7)
    - 1936 (Box 8)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 8A)
  - Materials on the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939
    - Unindentified Materials, Undated (Box 9–13)
    - Weekly Situation Reports
      - Nos. 2-20 (Box 14)
      - Nos. 21-52 (Box 15)
      - Nos. 53-77 (Box 16)
      - Nos. 78-98 (Box 17)
      - Nos. 99-131 (Box 18)
- Additional Material, 1935-1941; Accession 1997-M-149
  - Documents concerning military and economic relations between the Soviet Union and Germany, 1935-1941 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1930s; Accession 2001-M-046; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Khalepskii, I. A., and BT tanks, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 1-4)